[Music]
hello my name is H Peter boring and I
greet you a warm welcome to this session
on uh the exciting new page scription
tool for user acceptance testing that we
launch in preview in this release
so are you struggling with user
acceptance testing
today is it challenging getting a good
or even any test
coverage do track user acceptance tests
in
documents are you waiting for tedious
manual testing to complete go
live are the frequent updates causing
test
headaches would you like to run
acceptant tests as part of devops to
capture regressions already during
development or as part of
rollout and are you dreaming of
empowering Consultants or even customer
personas to capture and execute user
exceptions tests for better agility and
reduce
costs well then we have great news for
you because in this release we are
introducing a new tool allowing
customers and consultant buttons to
exactly do that easily record and play
user acceptance tests directly in the
business Central web client driving
higher test coverage and
Agility while reducing
costs we released this tool as a preview
in 2024 release way
one um so how can you use start trying
this tool out and give us
feedback well you access the page
scripting to from the settings
menu and that doesn't matter whether
it's online or on premise I have an
example of both
here now uh to use the two we have
separate permissions for recording and
for playing
scripts and so um the permission to
record is basically oped out by
default however since replay can
actually uh insert or change data in the
environment the permission to play has
to be granted to the
user and uh we actually right now
support uh playback both in production
and in uh sandboxes but we will warn if
you're trying to uh play scripts
recorded scripts in a production
environment so how do you you know go
about this well when you open the page
is description to it uh opens up as a uh
pane to the uh right side of the web
client just like the page inspector
tool and uh in that tool you can
initiate a new recording or you can open
a previously saved recording you both
have an option in the toolbar for doing
this but you can also use the buttons in
the welcome text that describes how to
use uh or getting started with this
tool
so uh when you then start uh a new
recording which is what I'm showing here
then uh the tool immediately enters the
recording State and the way you see that
is by this uh sort of a red blinking
Circle that you also see in the
screenshot here and that indicates a
recording basically the icons that we're
using here should be familiar to you
from sort of uh you know uh record and
and play uh experiences on dev
deves H you can also see that we haven't
really um recorded any steps yet so the
list of steps recorded is
empty you can then go about and perform
uh various steps so in this case we have
uh during the recording navigated to the
customer the customer's page was shown
and we invoked um a row on uh that list
and that will show up then in the
recorded steps in in the list
also the last step uh which is then
showing the customer card will be
highlighted and um is the active step
and for the last active step you have
some additional things you can do with
regards to to editing uh that step and
we'll talk about that during this
session then when you completed with
your recording you can hit stop uh and
then save it and you know you can even
restart a recording from the end to add
addition
steps now a core concept of user
acceptance uh testing is to verify an
expected outcome of performing a given
set of steps so to support this uh we uh
allow you to as part of the recording
insert so-called validation steps to
check that the outcome um to check the
outcome when you replay the recording
right and so to do this you can right
click a control a field here we have
right clicked the uh number uh in the
general fast Tab and you can see that um
you have a validate submenu and part of
that uh has an option for uh validating
whether the current value is 10,000 so
by invoking this option it will actually
insert a script uh sorry a step uh in
the script as we seeing here to validate
that the number indeed is
10,000
now if maybe it's not 10,000 that you
want right so but that was what was
there during the recording but maybe you
want to test it for another value uh or
maybe you want to test it for being
different than what it normally is so it
it fails uh you know for some reason you
can click the three dots to open up a
context menu on the step and select
properties and that will open up a
properties pain in the page scripting uh
pain and there you can set the value
that is being used for the validation
again you can see 10,000 here you even
have the choice of using various um
operators or choose between several
operators so you can for instance
compare so that the value is equal to or
greater than or less than
Etc then when you're done you can save
this script so that you basically
download it um scripts are saved in yaml
format and we'll talk uh more about that
at the end of of this session but once
you have a saved script you can share it
you can give it to someone else and they
can rerun that script of course for it
to work not just fail it needs to be run
in an environment similar to where it
was recorded right you have to have the
pages and objects and functionality to
be similar but that is also the intent
normally that you want to verify over
time that the beh behavior in a given
setup remains uh
correct
so uh let's have a look at our first
recording so let's jump to the web
client so here I am inside of the
business Central web client and as I
mentioned you invoke the tool in the
settings menu and we have pay scripting
option and also as mentioned you need to
have permissions to be able to use this
and of course I have that in this
session both for recording and for
playing back as we saw in the slides
when you open the page scripting tool
you have a getting started greeting here
and we would like to start a new
recording okay so here we now have the P
scripting tool um recording you see that
by the sort of blinking flashing red dot
here for recording that we saw in the
slide so I can now perform or record my
steps we see that no steps have been
recorded so let's start by opening the
sales
orders and we see that the tool will
capture that I I I navigated to sales
orders and that the sales orders page
actually showed up I can then go and
select an entry in the sales order list
and so now we have this sales order open
and maybe I want to validate something
here maybe I want to validate that the
contact is actually Robert uh towns so
I'm going to right click Robert towns
and I'm I'm going to go to the validate
menu and I'm going to say that you know
let's validate that the current value is
Robert towns and so that will insert a
step here that I would want to validate
Robert towns so this is our recording
for now let's uh stop the recording and
then go back to the slides so we saw how
easy it was uh to record a number of
steps and also insert validation but you
know that's great but of course we want
to be able to play those steps uh back
again to verify if the capture test
still runs for instance after an
update and so when you are in uh in
playback and this is an example this is
basically the the the script that I just
recorded um you have an action to play
we saw the record before but of course
when you want to play something you have
to press
play uh we support that uh instead of
playing that you can single step so uh
we can you can use the next or the
previous to go back and forth and
execute uh the steps right but it's
important to understand that when you go
back or the previous action there's no
undo in that you're just basically
redoing it you're going back to redo the
steps right there's no undo in
this you can also uh rewind to the
beginning right so if you if you stopped
the execution or if you if you uh uh
said next next next next next but not
all the way through and you want to
restart you can rewind to start and
basically uh you see in this view that
the last line is is gray and active that
is basically sort of the step indicator
for the active uh uh line right and that
is the one you're moving with previous
and next and and
Rewind um in this case the script is
actually failing so you get a
notification that it is H failing
and you uh apart from the the steps that
are passing I mean you get an indication
with the green check mark here for the
steps that passed but you also get a red
exclamation point for the step that fail
it will actually show you the error here
right so in this case I and I will show
you that later I changed the name a
little bit H so it's not the correct
name and of course that will fail in
playback so let's see how that works we
are back again in the web client and we
have the page scripting that we recorded
uh or the pay script that we recorded
before and uh I would like uh to
basically just reset to the beginning
here because I I would like to to play
it right and we kind of left in the last
step here so I I used the rewind to
start and then I also went back to sort
of my starting point which was uh in the
the rooll center here so I'm going to uh
press uh play and that is then going to
run the whole script I could have moved
one step ahead only uh but here I just
press play to record everything and in
this case everything is running right
because we haven't changed anything so
one of the things I I might be
interested in and that was what I showed
in the in the slides is that maybe I
want to validate to another value right
and so in this case let's not validate
to Rober but Rob towns right and that
will likely fail or that is the
expectation so uh let's just stop this
and Rewind was already rewind and go
back to home here so I'm at a starting
point and I'm going to run
again and so it's again going to perform
the task and as you see now the last
step of validation is failing and we're
told that we were expecting Rob towns
but we got Robert towns so this
basically shows you know how easy it is
to record a page script and replay it as
a unit as a user acceptance test now
these are simple scenarios uh but as I
men mentioned in the beginning you can
also open uh
recordings and so uh let's have a look
at some existing recording here this is
a little longer recording that will
navigate to sales orders uh it will then
filter down to the ad datum customer and
then it will open it up and you know
look up on the cell to customer number
and select something and close it down
and we can run that
again and we will see that that it run
through each step and in this case
everything completed right so this was a
little more advanced scenario of
validating a recorded user acceptance
test so when you want to play back a
script uh you can actually decide only
to run to a certain step right so if you
go to the context menu on the step you
want to run to you can select run to
here and then a playback will execute
and run only to that step and you see
that here that we have the green check
marks down until that step now if you
want to continue you can either press
play to just continue playing everything
or you can select uh to run to a later
step in the same
manner yeah so we saw how easy it was
not just to record uh but also to
play a user acceptance test that you
recorded in the page scripting tool when
you've done that maybe you want to share
that record recording and its result uh
we have something we call uh the
basically the playback lock uh you can
share that so there is in the toolbar
for the uh page scripting uh tool there
is an opportunity to to share copy a
link um and that link is
self-contained it basically includes um
the full recording and if you ran it it
will also include the state of that
recording and all of that is is hash in
a Bas 64 payload that might not mean
anything to you but basically it means
that the link that you're getting to
your environment will include a lot of
uh you know strange characters that um
is a very efficient representation of
this test case and the result and then
you can take this link and then you can
give it to someone else and they can you
know if they have access to that
environment of course they can invoke
that and they can see the page script as
well as the result maybe to uh further
investigate why this is failing in the
test so that was basically the you know
the basics of this but there's a lot
more so let's talk about uh all of the
advanced features that you have as
well so uh to begin with the page
scripting tool has its own uh clipboard
and uh this can be used to store results
that you get back during recording uh
steps
and reuse those
later in follow-up steps basically and
the way this works is again with the
context menu on fields uh whenever you
have a value you can go uh right click
during recording you will have the page
scripting context menu you can then
select a copy and that will copy it to
the page scripting clipboard that means
that at a later stage a separate step
where you need that value you can again
invoke the context menu but now you can
go to paste and as we see here in this
example we have a an an option to put in
the cell to customer name the datm
corporation we can then paste that in in
that next step right so that's a really
convenient way to reuse this to reuse
values across
steps uh related to that uh during a
recording that could also be certain
session information for instance the
user ID uh that you sometimes need in
certain uh tests so um in that scenario
similar to before you can go into the
context menu for page scripting and you
can now paste in on the session info the
user ID in this case it was the admin
right that might be relevant for certain
uh
scenarios then we have a number of uh of
Step branches uh the first one is what
we call conditional step branches so
sometimes a set of Step s only apply on
a given uh condition right so imagine
that you open a list uh page uh maybe if
the list page is empty you want to do
something different than if it has
content if it's empty maybe you want to
you know create a line whereas if it has
something maybe you just want to select
a line and check something right and so
um to to cater for that during a
recording you can uh again use um the
contact menu so here I'm on an empty um
list and you can see I go into the pay
script in context menu and I go to the
add conditional steps when option and
here it suggests that my possibility is
that when the row count is zero I can do
something I can insert a conditional uh
step so um imagine that we've done that
uh that will then insert in the list of
steps in the page scripting paint
this condition right so here it says
when control one uh row count is zero
and you can see that the steps below
that says no step is kind of nested
inside that's because now we created a a
branch or nesting where everything that
we record will happen only if that
condition is met and so here we have
scenarios that I show here that I ran a
a step that then became nested under
that conditional Branch right when you
then want to stop executing steps in
that Branch you select the end scope and
that goes out of the conditional branch
and that means that the subsequent steps
that you record will no longer be nested
under that condition but will happen
afterwards right so your total flow will
be something happens if a condition is
met then only then do something and then
when you're done with doing that go back
and continue uh the script yeah and
maybe I should mention that you can just
as we saw before and I actually have
that in the beginning here but I didn't
talk to it when you have that
conditional step in the properties pane
that you can invoke with the three dots
context menu on the step of course you
can change that to have a different
condition and with a different operator
so you can say that if it's more than
five rows you want to do something or
similar to
that let's jump to the related concept
uh of of branching but for optional
pages right so sometimes in a flow a
page will appear uh but it's
conditionally it's not always appearing
it's because of something else right and
here and again you can uh insert a
branch H but now you make that page that
appear an optional page so you see here
in the screenshot that I select from the
context menu on the step in the page
scripting pane to make that an optional
page and that basically means that all
of the steps that I record from there on
until I exit the branch will only happen
if that page is shown so we can see that
here I say that this page is optional um
for this case there's no properties it's
you know it's either showing or not um
and right now there's no steps then on
that page that appears when I record I
will do some steps and then when to I'm
done I'm going to say end scope and then
I can continue the recording to record
the steps if that page is not shown
right so that gives you again control
over um branchings in your recorded
steps by the way in the UI here you know
if you get very long scripts you can
collapse these n structures right that's
what I'm showing here you should be
familiar with that uh concept and that
just makes it a little bit easier to
read the overall
scripts then we talked a number of times
uh that you had the properties pain and
you could put in a value what I haven't
shown yet uh is that you can actually
also write an expression for very simple
calculations and we're using power
effect as the expression language and
you might be familiar with power effects
from from the Power Platform or or Excel
and U in the uh properties pain there is
a reference uh to the power FX uh you
know
syntax um and in addition to power F we
also give you uh three top level objects
that you can use the Expression you can
call into the clipboard that we talked
about before to pull out values there
you can call into something that we call
parameters which are really variables
for the script and we'll talk about
those later and you can also access the
session info that I spoke about before
so to show a couple of examples here
that you see you could pick out the um
you know maybe the customer card number
the number on the customer card maybe
you save that to the clipboard and in
your flow you just want to see whether
that's being incremented uh by one uh it
could also be that you want to generate
a random name as part of generating a
new object to have some uniqueness maybe
you want to have a a semi- random name
so that could be concatenating the the
the customer with today's date or or
time or something like that then also um
sometimes when you are executing uh uh
steps or you know logic in in business
Central maybe it takes some extra time
maybe it calls to an external web
service where there can be some time
happening right and to not time out uh
and fail during playback you can
actually tell during recording that you
expect things to take a little longer
time so we have the option of setting in
a step an extra step which is a weight
step and um you can go to the pro it
will default to 1 second or th000
milliseconds and you can go to the
properties and you can change that to
whatever 10 seconds or something like
that in general you know you shouldn't
really so so the the weight States here
are more to cater for the scenarios
where you want to avoid the time M but
it's not something that you really want
to use a lot that's that's you know if
there's no need for it don't use it then
we talked about that uh the scripts are
really stored in the yaml format um and
that's like um you know metad driven
format for for clients here and um the
the nice thing about having a yaml as
the format is that it's kind of a
standardized format right and that helps
in editing scenarios and it helps in in
devop scenarios as well uh I have an
example here of a script and the high
level structure of the script is that
there's like a header with the name and
the description of this then we capture
the role that is being used uh to ex to
record the script we do that because the
you everything is ried on sort of the
controls so so the script will point to
controls in the UI and whether they show
up or not will typically depend on the
role because there can be a role
customizations that can also be
personalizations of course um and then
we have each of the steps and some of
the steps can be nested if we have these
branches that I that I spoke about um
and each step can have there can be
different types of steps and they are
covered in the metadata for the steps I
won't go into detail on that but that
will give you a high level understanding
of of the
content now there are a couple of
scenarios powerful scenarios that we
currently only support in yaml so you
have to go to edit them in the yaml H
they are supported when you then play
them in the client but there isn't a uh
page in uh s page is scripting user
experience in the client for doing these
things only in y and the first one is
that you can as I mentioned a little
earlier when we talked about the
Expressions you can actually
parameterize scripts so that's basically
the equivalent of setting some variables
that you can then use throughout the
script to to to you know cater for um
basically make it more robust and make
it easier if you want to change that
value to not have to change it in many
places in the script but just in the
parameter list and so in this scenario
you you know in the example you see we
have the parameters uh Noe in the um
yaml file and we specify a parameter
called customer list number where we set
the value to uh
10,000 uh and then in the steps you can
use that so you can call up the
parameters collection so here in the
step shown we set the value by looking
up in the parameters um collection and
pick out the customer list number from
there and they will then of course
insert 10,000 when we execute disc
script and as I said you can use this uh
in the expressions in the UI as well so
you could do the same parameters.
customer list number from within the UI
then uh you cannot so a common scenario
uh and we'll talk about that later is
also that it can be beneficial to make
small scripts that are more um specific
and then tie them together in a suite
basically where you execute the scripts
in a sequence but there's no way to to
really edit there's not a lot of editing
um support yet inside of the web client
experience of the page scripting tool H
and we don't support any kind of sweet
uh management from in there but you can
actually do that in yaml and only in yam
of course and so um you can bundle
multiple scripts uh there and the way it
works is that um you use a the include
command in the script here and so in the
example here you see that we have two
includes and basically you point to the
script file right so we're pointing to
two different scripts right here and the
sequence of course matters it's going to
go top down when it when it executes and
you can use the parameters I just talked
to talked about to um to reuse variables
across uh the scripts of course the
scripts that you include inside of those
they need to use those parameters as
well for this to work right so basically
the way this works is that you have
separate scripts and then you create a
new script which only caters for being
sort of the the the the suite and then
that's the one you execute and on on
load time it will pull in uh the other
um included
scripts okay let's uh round off with a
little bit of best practices and and um
and known things so first off um I
showed a couple of scenarios where we
select in the list and you probably saw
that we we we don't track you know the
actual instance that we are selecting
like a in invoice number 47 or something
like that you you basically pick uh from
the from the top right and so if you
want to match a specific one it can be a
good idea during recording to to try to
set a filter in the list because we are
capturing that filter um to make sure
that the line that you're interested in
is shown at the top and then it will be
selected uh during the replay as well
because it will apply the same filters
also when you are relying on entities
you know maybe you need to use a
customer or something like that in a
script for a sales order if you want to
be in control it can be a good idea to
uh create a separate script for creating
that customer so that you're not allow
you know relying on the fact of that
being there in in an environment where
the data changes and this is also a
scenario where that site concept that I
talked about before could come in handy
where you make one recording for
creating the customer and one recording
for using um a customer in the um sales
order and then you create a suite tying
those together
right uh and that's basically what I
what I just said here that it's also
good to break down the flow in smaller
smaller pieces
then a couple of things uh that are good
to know uh the as I said the tool is in
preview now um please give us feedback
on yamama and uh on ideas on this
probably the biggest shortcomings at
this point it is the first version right
and it is in preview so there will be uh
things but um there aren't that many
that there's not a lot of support for
during recording to to change the steps
right that hey I want to delete these
two and rearrange that's also because
and the the the the sequence is
important right so you cannot just Omid
a step in the middle but there are
things that that would be nice to be
able to do that you cannot yet do with
with editing the steps uh also as I
mentioned you can only build Suites in
yaml not in the client and then I
mentioned in the complete beginning that
one of the nice things about this would
be that you can uh run run the scripts
play the scripts in pipelines so as part
of development or as part of uh sort of
roll out of cicd you can actually
execute these to see if you have any
regressions and that's something that
we're working on but uh we and um it's
not yet supported to run that you can
only run them in the client at this
point then there's a couple of uh sort
of known issues we're not recording
designer interactions uh you know if you
open up the incline designer U report
previews cannot be closed um we don't
handle notifications or multiple not
notifications that that well um we
really need the next previous buttons on
cards to be there if you have fields
that are called so basically we're
relying on references to controls in the
UI with a name and if you put fields in
different places with the same name we
might not find the right uh place also
sometimes you have uh messages or
confirmation dialogues Etc that can H
pop up in sort of you know different
different flows before or after a page
and that can create some race conditions
that where you record it in one way and
when you replay it it actually happens
in a different sequence and and that
could lead to the replay failing so
that's something to be aware of as well
and then it's super important to mention
that um you know what is this tool not
because you might be familiar with uh
you know just general um test tools for
web pages HTML automation tools and this
is not an HTML automation tool right so
we cannot automate uh control edings
like charts or any embedded uh content
like powerbi or power apps or something
like that or anything outside of
business Central where you want to
orchestrate some kind of end to end flow
that goes out
outside it it is riing on knowing about
the controls and knowing about BC but
that is also what makes it stronger than
an HTML automation tool for some of the
scenarios that involve a business
Central uh controls um it is I'm not
covering it in this video but it is
worth mentioning also that you can
actually use this tool together with
some of these sort of more generic tool
to actually uh plug in this and execute
uh in a bigger end to end scenario and
by the way remember as usual there's
lots of resources available you know you
can ask us questions on yamama you can
join office hours on various topics you
can submit your ideas to the idea size
Etc so use the resources to give us
feedback anyway I hope you uh found the
you know I think this is an awesome Tool
uh I uh I really urge you to try it out
and give us feedback uh really hope that
you like it and I thank you for joining
this session
bye